<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The searching out the deceit, and bringing the deceivers words and actions to the light, to be proved and tryed with the light, which is just, judging and condemning that which is acted or spoken contrary to the light</title>
            <author>Aldam, Thomas, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A894C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19042</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12670773</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12670773</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65483</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26639)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65483)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 679:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The searching out the deceit, and bringing the deceivers words and actions to the light, to be proved and tryed with the light, which is just, judging and condemning that which is acted or spoken contrary to the light</title>
                  <author>Aldam, Thomas, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Tho. Aldam.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:65483:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65483:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Searching out the DECEIT, and bringing the Deceivers words and actions to the Light, to be proved and tryed with the Light, which is juſt, judging and condemning that which is acted or ſpoken contrary to the Light.</head>
            <p>This is given forth for the clearing of the Truth from Slanders caſt upon it, and for no other end. The ground and cauſe of our publiſhing this forth in print to the Nation, is, we finding many ſlanders and falſe reports in Books publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Nation, by one who is called by name <hi>Henry Walker,</hi> which calls himſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt; and alſo by <hi>George Horton,</hi> called, <hi>The Faithful Scout,</hi> but is found deceitful. In whoſe books, many groundleſs falſe reports and ſlanders are tryed and proved by many witneſſes, who have gone to ſearch out the matter, and have found them that publiſhed them, that they could give no ground for the falſe reports which was caſt upon a people whom every one which is out of the fear of God nick-names, and ſcornſully calls <hi>QUAKERS;</hi> and they are their mark, as <hi>David</hi> was, amongſt ſuch as God was not in their thoughts, the proud and loſty, which goes before the fall: and ſuch as the Lord regards, and trembles at his word, ſuch the world regards not, as you may read in <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> And they ſhall ſpeak all monner of evil of you, for my Names ſake, ſaith Chriſt. And they ſhall be given ever to believe lyes, ſaith the Spirit that gave forth the Scriptures, and we do ſee them fulfilled. And they ſhall bend their tongues like a bowe to tell Lyes, ſaying, <hi>Report, and we will report it;</hi> and this We finde fulfilled in our days, and loading with reproaches the people of God, as it was done unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> which was a <hi>Quaker,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Heb. 12, 21.</hi> but reproaches are our riches. So to clear the Truth from ſlanders cast upon him who is called <hi>George Fox,</hi> and others, was we moved to write and print theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that all the ſimple ones, and honest hearted, may ſee, our end of print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to clear the Truth from falſe accuſations caſt upon it; and that all things may be brought to the light by it, to be tryed and proved: for with the light which Christ Jeſus hath enlightned thee withal, we ſee theſe Spirits that we have tryed, to be like Prieſt, like People, all uttering forth reproachful ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and evil reports, not having any ground which to us they make appear for what they have done or ſaid againſt the innocent; who are found ſlanderers in the dark: but their deeds are brought forth to the light, to all who have an eye open to ſee them. <hi>2 Theſſ. 2.11, 12. Jer. 9.2. 1 Tim. 4.3. Hoſ. 4.2. and the Scriptures fulfilled,</hi> Hoſ. <hi>4 9. A horrible filthy thing is committed in the land,</hi> Jer. 5.30, 31.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the yeer 1655.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65483:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CErtaine ſlanders, and falſe reports and reproaches being caſt upon him, who is of the world called <hi>George Fox</hi> and others, and an honorable Woman in the Lord, whoſe being is in the <hi>North,</hi> one who is called Colonell <hi>Fells</hi> Wife; who was ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and reproached with falſe reports, by one <hi>Henry Walker</hi> neer <hi>Weſtminſter Abbey</hi> dwelling, the truth cleared from the falſe accuſations, and the falſe ſlanders denyed, which was giving a Bunch of Ribbons to him above mentioned.</p>
            <p>Two men whoſe names are <hi>Henry Clark</hi> and <hi>William Wilſon,</hi> was ſent the 7 day of the firſt month to querie, to know and find out the grounds of the ſlanders, that upon the truth it might not reſt, but be caſtoff: ſo they went to the Printer, and found that <hi>Henry Walker</hi> had given thoſe things in to be Printed, the falſe reports caſt upon <hi>George Fox</hi> afore-mentioned, and <hi>VValker</hi> promiſed to thoſe two men, that if <hi>George Fox</hi> would give it under his hand, that he did abſolutely deny the reports and ſlanders which <hi>VValker</hi> had caſt upon him and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to the Nation in his newes bookes, the ſaid <hi>VValker</hi> ſaid he would prove it. Whereupon <hi>George Fox</hi> did give it under his hand, and in his writing did deny all his ſlanders, falſe reports and Reproaches; and three men went downe to the ſaid <hi>VValker</hi> to his houſe, upon the 8 day of the firſt month, whoſe names are called <hi>Thomas Aldam, John Aviſon,</hi> and <hi>Henry Clark,</hi> expecting to have found <hi>VValker</hi> to have done according to his promiſe, to have proved the ſlanders, which he had promiſed to two men to do, but did not, and when the three men came there, and did deliver the writing which <hi>George Fox</hi> had ſet his hand to, wherein he did deny all the falſe ſlanders, and falſe reports caſt upon him: The ſaid 3 men demanded of the ſaid <hi>VValker</hi> to prove the ſlanders and reports caſt upon <hi>George</hi> and others, (according to his promiſe) but <hi>VValker</hi> denyed to prove it there, and ſaid he would not mention any ones name; and bade the men be gone out of his houſe, and denyed the name which he had mentioned, as he had publiſhed in his Booke that a Gentlewoman had reported it; and then ſaid after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that a Gentleman did report it, and after denyed that the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman did report it, before <hi>Henry Clark</hi> and <hi>VVilliam VVilſon,</hi> this thing he denyed which he had publiſhed in print to the Nation, neither would mention the mans name nor any other which reported thoſe ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to him.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65483:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And here we do ſee him to be a liar, and a truce-breaker, ſaying, Report, and we will report it, as they did by <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> as you may read <hi>Jer.</hi> 20. And read 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. Thy firſt ſlander <hi>Henry Walker,</hi> thou ſcornfully calls the people of God in thy printed paper <hi>Quakers; Moſes</hi> the Judge of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> he exceedingly feared and Quaked, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.21. And he was reproached, and here thou ſhewes what Generation thou art in.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, thou giveſt the Term of the old ring-leaders, So it was ſaid to <hi>Paul. Act.</hi> 24.5. And here thou ſhewes in whoſe ſteps thou walkeſt.</p>
            <p>The third falſe report and ſlander is, thou ſayeſt it is ſaid that <hi>George Fox</hi> ſeduced Colonel <hi>Fells wife,</hi> which thing is falſe, and all ſeducers he denies; and thou who art a ſlanderer, nor thy ſaiers, nor thou ſeducer art not worthy her name to mention, who is honorable in the Lord: and many unſavory ſpeeches thou haſt uttered forth, which thou ſaid thou heard of a Gentlewoman; and after denied it, for in the living truth of God, Judge <hi>Fells</hi> wife is, which is the Judge of all ſuch falſe accuſers, and ſlanderers, Read thy ſelf, and ſee the Scripture fulfilled upon thee, <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9 4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.28. <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.19.</p>
            <p>And the fourth falſe report and ſlander is, that the ſaid Woman which the ſaid <hi>Walker</hi> denyed, ſaid that ſhe heard him boaſting of his Favours, and Bunch of Ribbons about <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> which he had from Colonell <hi>Fells</hi> wife, and others: which all is falſe: But this is like unto <hi>Walkers</hi> Preaching, who with the dark world is called a Miniſter; who is proved to be a liar and a ſeducer, as he ſpeakes of, ſeeking to draw many to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to his evil reports, from the truth, and againſt it. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. 1 Joh. 2.26, 27. And as for ſlandering Judge <hi>Fells</hi> Wife, for giving him a Bunch of Ribbons, or others, ſuch unſavory things and actions he denies to boaſt with, and ſhe abhors thy words, who art a ſcandalous fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and all ſuch falſe ſlanders which thou caſts upon the Innocent, to make them appeare odious in the eyes of the world, but the Lord is their revenge, and doth preſerve them from the Seed of evil doers, to whom be all Praiſe for ever. And becauſe that Judge <hi>Fells</hi> Wife goes among the people of God, which waits upon the Lord God in their meetings, which is the cauſe that makes thee <hi>Walker,</hi> and the Heathens to rage and utter forth your envy againſt the righteous Seed, as your Generation ever did; and of them that ſpeak evil, and ſo fulfill Chriſts words. <hi>Jud.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou <hi>Walker</hi> ſaith there was divers ſtoryes told of him, and thou ſpeakes of a Gentlewoman having a Ribbon tyed about her hand, who was coming to a place where they met, <hi>Henry Walker</hi> we charge thee to name the place where that meeting was, and the names of ſome which was there, and where they dwell that ſaw it, or let thy mouth be ſtopped for ever, and be thou warned, leſt the Lord make thee a ſudden example to all ſlanderers, who falſly accuſe the innocent. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.4.</p>
            <p>And thou ſpeakes of the Womans maid tying a Ribbon about her hand; and about tying a Ribbon about her husbands wreſt, which thou
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65483:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Walker</hi> ſayeſt did deſire to go to <hi>Fox,</hi> which all the ſlanders and falſe reports is denyed, and for medling with any ſuch ſilly fooliſh doings; and many unſavory words which are not worth mentioning, which thou haſt printed, who art found a fit fellow for ſuch workes of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And thou ſpeaks of the Ribbon was caſt in the fire and ſtunk: Now <hi>Walker</hi> we do demand of thee who haſt given out theſe unſavory expreſſions, and haſt given them forth in print into the Nation, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to us what is the name of this Gentlewoman, and the maid, and the name of her husband, the Country they dwell in, and what towne they dwell in, and the place where theſe things was done, and who ſaw it, and where they dwell, that all thy works and actions may be brought unto the light to be proved; ſo in this thing manifeſt thy ſelf, for with the children of the light thou art ſeen, who ſees thee made known to the Nation, to be a liar and ſlanderer upon record to be noted, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.14. who art of thy Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44. Who ſhalt have thy part in the Lake, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. For all ſuch fooliſh things <hi>George</hi> denyes, and the ſlanders.</p>
            <p>And in the fifth ſlanders thou haſt put forth that ſome thinks that this <hi>Fox</hi> is a popiſh prieſt, thy thoughts and theirs be vaine. <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.26. For all Popiſh wayes he denyes.</p>
            <p>And again thou ſayeſt that ſome thinks he hath not wit enough to take a deſigne for the Papiſts, here thou art hearing reports, and ſaying we will report them, whoſe thoughts are vaine, who know him not with your thinking nor your thoughts, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.26.</p>
            <p>In the ſixt ſlander, thou ſayſt that ſome are confident there be witches amongſt them; here again <hi>Henry Walker</hi> we charge and command thee in the preſence of the Lord God, to mention the names of that ſome, and let that ſome mention the names of thoſe witches, which that ſome ſayes they are confident, that witch-craft may be found out, elſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thy ſelf to be him that ſlanders in the ſecret, for witch-craft we deny, for truth is now ſlandered to be witch-craft, with the ſeed of evil doers, who fails in their confidence. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.16.</p>
            <p>And again <hi>Henry Walker,</hi> thou ſpeakes of a Gentlewoman coming to <hi>George Fox,</hi> telling of his haire, and buttons, and thou ſaid the ſaid <hi>George</hi> anſwered him ſcornfully; which is falſe, for no ſcorner he is, and his buttons are neither ſilk nor ſilver, how fain wouldſt thou take an occaſion againſt him, who the Faſhions of the world, and the vanities of it doth deny? who in that place at <hi>Whitehall</hi> that day did give an anſwer ſufficient to ſatisfie any rational man, as touching his haire, in my hearing in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> who was then preſent with him, who am call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the name of <hi>Thomas Aldam,</hi> a witneſs of it againſt the falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <p>And thou <hi>Walker</hi> ſaid he abuſed divers others, that was falſe, he abuſed none, but told them the truth, thou maiſt as well ſay now we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe thee in telling thee truth, to cleare the truth from thy ſlanders.</p>
            <p>And again <hi>Heny Walker,</hi> thou ſayſt he called a Miniſter a liar, thou
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65483:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſaid thou was a Miniſter, and thou was proved to be liar, for thou ſaid he denied the feare of God, and it was witneſſed againſt thee that he did not ſpeake ſuch a word, but it was ſaid by <hi>George Fox,</hi> that thou made proſelytes, and the fear of God was not denied by him called <hi>George Fox,</hi> but witneſſed by him, exhorting many to fear the Lord God in my hearing, and many others, <hi>Tho. Aldam,</hi> and to depart from pride and filthineſs, and to come into the fear of God. And again thou denied and ſaid Chriſt Jeſus doth not enlighten every one that comes into the world, and here thou art a liar and a falſe witneſs, for <hi>John</hi> ſaid who was a true witneſs, that Chriſt Jeſus was the true light, which lighteth every one that cometh into the world. <hi>John</hi> 1.9. And thou ſaiſt he doth not, and here thou art proved a liar, and one that beares falſe witneſs, and thy voyce is denied and Judged with record.</p>
            <p>And again thou ſaiſt that <hi>George</hi> and the reſt was thruſt down the ſtayres; there was a Rude raſh unſavory fellow, in a diſorderly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, came without any Juſt command, and tare <hi>George</hi> clothes, and gave out many unſavory expreſſions, which many of the houſe-hold was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of to ſee the thing done, and did diſlike of his practice, for he had no command to do what he did to <hi>George;</hi> from any Juſt autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, for after he was put down by that Rude fellow, <hi>George</hi> was taken up again into the hall, and other friends with him, and the Rude fellow condemned for doing what he had done to <hi>George</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>And <hi>George</hi> and others went from thence in a peaceable and orderly maner. From them who loves peace and unity, who doth ſee the hand of the Lord God turned againſt all ſuch, who are ſlanderers &amp; falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, who are ſwift to hear evil reports of the innocent, to report them, to bring the innocent into reproach and contempt with the world, which is our riches, as the ſeed of evil doers did, and to thee and you all it is the word of the Lord God, thee, and you to warn, therefore be thou warned, <hi>Henry Walker,</hi> and all of you warned, and turn to the Lord God from perſecuting of the innocent, leaſt the Lord cut you off in the day of his firie wrath.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Aldam.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <p>TO us whoſe names are called <hi>Thomas Aldam, George Rennold,</hi> and <hi>John Rouſe,</hi> a Paper was brought; which is titled the faithful Scout; making known to the Nation divers things done and ſaid in the Nation, from the 2 day of <hi>March,</hi> till the ninth, 1654. Publiſhed by <hi>George Horton,</hi> and Printed by <hi>Robert VVood,</hi> in London, in which Paper called the faithfull Scout, we find many impudent expreſſions, aſperſions, and reproachfull words, caſt upon the people of God, which Scornefully the world calls <hi>Quakers,</hi> which faithfull Scout ſo titled, is ſeen with the light which comes from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in us made manifeſt, to be an unreaſonable man, and not to have faith, in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65483:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>whom the lying and falſe accuſing Spirit of darkneſs Ruleth, as his declaration in his Paper doth make it appeare, and their own words ſpoken to our face, whoſe names are above mentioned, who for the clearing of the truth, from falſe reports, and falſe accuſations, was moved to go to the Printers houſe to enquire for <hi>George Horton,</hi> and to examine the matter, demanding of them what ground they had for to Print and Publiſh ſuch falſe reports, ſcandals, and untruths to the Nation, caſt upon the people of God ſcornfully called <hi>Quakers</hi> by the world. The Printer and the ſaid <hi>George Horton,</hi> ſaid they had authority to Print re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, and what words they pleaſed, and what they had Printed againſt us this weeke, they would Print twice as much the next, if we was not ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: then I who am called <hi>Thomas Aldam</hi> ſaid, What uncivility doſt thou ſee by us? the Printer ſaid, you are impudent fellowes, and come to make tumultes about my dore, and was in great rage; I ſaid we came to enquire of thee, and <hi>George Horton,</hi> to make this appear which to the Nation is publiſhed, to be truth, or elſe with the truth are you wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt, to be ſlanderers in the dark, and falſe accuſers of the innocent, and do require of you to anſwer me.</p>
            <p>Then I ſaid to <hi>George Horton</hi> and the Printer, you have reported and publiſhed to the Nation, that there are many impudent creatures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding in and about the City of London, which entitle themſelves <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> and have ſeduced many innocent people; then I who am called <hi>Tho. Aldam,</hi> asked them what impudence or wicked thing was done by them; or what had they ſeen: their anſwer was, They heard ſay one went naked in Smith-field, I ſaid, Didſt thou ſee it? he ſaid no, but a lad told him ſo. Then ſaid I, Thou here charges them with ſeduceing people, what is ſeducing? But the man fell into much bitterneſs and wrath, and bid me be gone from his dore, then ſaid I, Friend thou ſayſt, thou was credibly informed, that one went naked into Smith-field amongſt the hay carts, and that ſome demanded of him, why he walked in that Beaſtly garbe, and to this many can witneſs againſt thee, that there was no hay carts there, for it was about 9 of the Clock at night, and that was falſe, and a lye, who art of thy father, read <hi>John</hi> 8.44. Then I ſaid to the Printer, Doſt thou call it a beaſtly garb, for a man to go naked in obedience to the command of God? wouldſt thou not have called <hi>Iſaiah</hi> a beaſt if <hi>Iſaiah</hi> had been here, or thou in his time, who went three years naked? the Printer ſaid it was a beaſtly part, for him to go ſo, here I who am called <hi>Tho. Aldam</hi> ſaid, I charge thee to be a Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, in ſpeaking evil of the people of God. And whereas thou ſaiſt that ſome asked him wherefore he went in that beaſtly garbe, being naked, and his anſwer was, that God had commanded him, and that a carter ſaid he had command to whip him into better manners, I ſaid, didſt thou friend who art the Printer, or <hi>George Horton</hi> hear or ſee this, or who did which you can name? their anſwer was, they did neither ſee it, or hear it, ſomething was true, they heard ſay one went naked, and for the other, they had liberty to Print what words they pleaſed. Now for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65483:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>the truths ſake, was we three moved to enquire after this matter, that no lye nor falſe ſlanders, and evil reports might reſt upon the truth, to the clearing of the truth to the underſtanding of all who have an eye open to ſee with, what ſlandering falſe accuſing, and evil reports have been caſt upon the truth, By the ſpirit of lyes, and ſlanders, whoſe throates are become an open ſepulchre, ſaying, Report, and I will report it: and that you may ſee theſe mens ground of report, was from a lad, or boy, as they declared to us, which one of them, the Printer or the other, called credible information, to which boy we went, and did require of him to let us know what he had declared to the Printer, &amp; he ſaid, Nothing at all; and here with the light which comes from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which is made manifeſt in us, we ſee, comeprehend and Judge the lying falſe accuſing ſpirits, who in their envy have uttered againſt the truth, to render the people of God odious to the world, now to all friends in the light, and to the light in all conſciences I ſpeake, which with it the deeds is ſeen and Judged, to it I appeale, that with it you may ſee, and try the ſpirits, and with the Children of the light bear witneſs againſt all ſuch as report lyes, and Print lyes, and falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, who ſay they have authority to do what is done, but woe and miſery is their portion, who uſurp authority to report lyes and Print them, to make others to believe their lyes and evil reports, as theſe two men have done, whoſe names are <hi>Robert Wood,</hi> and <hi>George Horton,</hi> which with the ſpirit of truth are Judged, &amp; the faithfull Scout is found unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, without faith, in the unreaſonable nature, for unreaſonable men have not faith, of which ſort are theſe falſe accuſers, who have uttered forth their folly, who cannot prove the things to be truth they have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely declared to the Nation, but are found reporting the evil imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of their own hearts: and the man which went naked, is a ſigne of their nakedneſs, and a ſigne to all unbelievers, liars, and falſe ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, in the dark, who the innocent perſecute, that their deeds and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are naked before the Lord God, and their nakedneſs appears, and folly is made manifeſt to all the children of the light, who are ſet for ſignes and wonders, among the impudent creatures which hate the light, whoſe deeds are evil, and the children of the light hate, as they ever did, but woe and miſery is coming, and their portion they muſt receive with all liars, and falſe accuſers; therefore now while you have time repent, leaſt the Lord cut you off in his fierce wrath, and make you a ſudden example, you who the innocent have falſely accuſed, for with the Simple eye are you ſeen, and with it Judged, from one who is a friend to the eſtabliſhing of righteouſneſs, and the ſearching out deceit, and to lay open the abomination of theſe who are titled faithful Scouts, and men giving perfect intelligence of actions done and ſaid, but are found imperfect, and unfaithfull men, in receiving the falſe reports in theſe things above mentioned, but theſe imperfect men, and unfaithfull, who numbered the Innocent amongſt the tranſgreſſers, and evil doers, are diſcovered, which have loadened them with evil reporaches, which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65483:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>are falſe, and the truth is cleared from the falſe accuſations caſt upon the Innocent, to that of God in all conſciences to be manifeſt, with which I am one, a friend to your Soules; for the eſtabliſhing of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgment, and ſweeping the land of evil doers, who are Slanderers of the juſt, from one whoſe name is called</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Aldam.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>But one I am with juſtice, which is a terrour to evil doers, and upon them lays hold, and ſets the innocent free, and them preſerves in peace from the hands of all unjuſt Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, who ſmite with the tongue and fiſt of wickedneſs, and the ſeed of God perſecutes, as the ſeed of evil doers ever did.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
